okemtutor.org question of the day
[Music]
this question we're going to do
nitration it's with hno3 h2so4 and the
Benzene ring so first let's draw the
Lewis structure of our hno3
you can see that we have a negative sign
on the oxygen neutral oxygen with the
double bond o and an o h with a couple
lone pairs next let's draw our h2so4
it's just a 4 is electrophilic so we can
go attack it
we're going to go for the proton and
redraw our hno3 which now is going to
have an oh2 plus so that's going to be
our leaving group
now that we have our leaving group and
we have our HS of four minus we can have
the H2O leave and that's going to leave
behind an NO2 that's positively charged
onwards we can see that we have our NO2
that's positively charged the nitrogen
is electron